<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A looking-glass for the Jews wherein they may clearly see that the Messiah is come, by the prophets in the Old Testament (above sixteen hundred years since) and the manifest testimonies since. And also, they may see their own blindness and ignorance of their own prophets, and of the Messiah unto this day. By which my desire is, they may turn to him, that their eyes may be opened, that they may see him whom they have pierced. By G. F. To which is added, a paper writ formerly to the Jews who assemble in Bevers-Marks, London, to be read and considered by them; with a few queries for them to answer. By G.W.</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40213</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827450</idno>
  <idno type="VID">31868</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240885795</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1859</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215642</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827450</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99827450e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40213)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31868)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1864:37)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A looking-glass for the Jews wherein they may clearly see that the Messiah is come, by the prophets in the Old Testament (above sixteen hundred years since) and the manifest testimonies since. And also, they may see their own blindness and ignorance of their own prophets, and of the Messiah unto this day. By which my desire is, they may turn to him, that their eyes may be opened, that they may see him whom they have pierced. By G. F. To which is added, a paper writ formerly to the Jews who assemble in Bevers-Marks, London, to be read and considered by them; with a few queries for them to answer. By G.W.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>G.F. = George Fox, the elder.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Jews --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31868:1"/>
            <p>A Looking-Glass FOR THE JEWS: Wherein they may clearly see that the Messiah is come, by the Prophets in the <hi>Old Testament</hi> (above Sixteen Hundred Years since) and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest Testimonies since.</p>
            <p>And also, they may see their own Blindness and Ignorance of their own Prophets, and of the <hi>Messiah</hi> unto this day.</p>
            <p>By which my desire is, they may turn to him, that their Eyes may be opened, that they may see him whom they have pierced.</p>
            <p>By <hi>G. F.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which is added, a Paper writ formerly to the JEWS who assemble in <hi>Bevers-Marks, London,</hi> to be read and considered by them; With a few <hi>Queries</hi> for them to Answer.</p>
            <p>By <hi>G. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>And thou <hi>Bethlehem Ephratah</hi> art little to be among the Thousands of <hi>Judah,</hi> yet out of thee shall be come forth unto me, that shall be the Ruler in <hi>Israel,</hi> whose Goings-forth have been from the Beginning, and from Everla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing, <bibl>
                  <hi>Mic. 5.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1674.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:31868:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:31868:2"/>
            <head>A Perfect and Plain TESTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONY to the <hi>JEWS,</hi> that the <hi>MESSIAH</hi> is come, according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>DAniel</hi> was a man greatly beloved of God, who interpreted <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezar</hi>'s Dream: And <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezar</hi>'s Dream concerned himself, and the whole Monarchy, the Head of Gold; and concerned the <hi>Persian</hi>-Monarchy, the Breast of Silver; and concerned the <hi>Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>-Monarchy, the Belly and Thighs of Brass; and concerned the <hi>Roman</hi>-Monarchy, the Legs of Iron, and the Feet of Iron and Clay: And the breaking of all these to pieces as the Chaff of the Summer Threshing-Floor, and the Wind carrying them away, that no place for them was found: And it was the Stone that smote the Image of Gold, &amp;c. and be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:31868:3"/> came a great Mountain, that filled the whole Earth? And is not this Stone the <hi>Messiah?</hi> For <hi>Daniel</hi> saith, <hi>Whom ye do believe as a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet and Beloved of God, in the dayes of these Kings shall the God of Heaven set up a Kingdom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 2.44.</note>
               <hi>which shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stroyed</hi> (mark, in the dayes of these four Monarchies) And the Kingdom shall not be left to other People; but it shall break in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to pieces and consume all these Kingdoms, and it shall stand forever; The Stone which was cut out of the Mountain without Hands it shall break into pieces the Brass, and the Clay and Iron, the Silver and the Gold Monarchies. Now <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> did say to <hi>Daniel, Of a Truth his God was the God of Truth, and the God of Gods, and the King of Kings, &amp;c.</hi> So now, consider, was not <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>buchadnezar</hi> beyond you in your Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief? And did not the <hi>Messiah</hi> come in the dayes of these four Monarchies, and set up his Kingdom above Sixteen Hundred Years since? And are not those four Monarchies dashed in pieces by the Stone which should come in their dayes? Was not <hi>Daniel</hi> a true Prophet, and <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi>'s Dream true upon the four Monarchies? And did not the God of Truth reveal these Secrets to him? So if ye do believe that <hi>Daniel</hi> was
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:31868:3"/> a true Prophet, and <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi>'s Dream true, and God did reveal the Secrets of it to <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the Gold, and Silver, and Brass, and Iron, &amp; Clay Monarchies were broken to pieces by the Stone which should become a great Mountain, and should fill the whole Earth; then you must believe that the <hi>Messi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> is come, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.44. And did not <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>buchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezar,</hi> in the Vision of himself to be the Tree which was hewen down, confess to the God of Heaven, and extol him, and lifted up his Eyes to Heaven, and blessed and prais<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Most High, and honoured him that lived forever; <hi>whose Dominion is an Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Dominion, and his Kingdom is from Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration to Generation.</hi> And mark that, and see if ye see this <hi>Kingdom</hi> that is <hi>everlasting, and Dominion</hi> from <hi>generation</hi> to <hi>generation:</hi> And see if you can see this in your Generation; And how can ye see this, unless you come to this Stone; and this Kingdom which God set up in the days of these four Monarchies, which should never have an End? For you know, ye had a Kingdom before those four Monarchies, which had an End.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Daniel</hi> in his Vision, Chap. 7.13. saw the Kingdom of God, who saw one like the Son of Man, and there was given him Dominion and Glory, and a Kingdom, that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:31868:4"/> all People, Nations and Languages should serve him; his Dominion is an Everlasting Dominion, and shall not pass away; and his Kingdom shall not be destroyed: Now you know yours past away: And the Saints should take this Kingdom, that is, the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified Ones.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Daniel</hi> heard one Saint speak to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>How long shall be the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion concerning the Daily Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 8.13.</note>
               <hi>and the Transgression of Desolation, to give both the Sanctuary &amp; the Host to be trod under feet? He said to me, Ʋnto Two Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Three Hundred Dayes, then shall the Sanctuary be cleansed.</hi> Now, do you cast up this time, and number these Dayes or Years, and see in what time your selves be in <hi>Daen.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. while <hi>Gabriel</hi> the Angel speaks to him, and tells <hi>Daniel,</hi> that <hi>he was greatly beloved, and to give him Skill and Ʋn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, &amp;c.</hi> And sayes to him, <hi>Seventy Weeks were determined upon his People, and upon the Holy City, to finish the Transgression, &amp; to make an End of Sin</hi> [mark] <hi>and to bring in Everlasting Righteousness, and to seal up the Vision &amp; Prophecy, and to anoint the Most Holy; know therefore and understand, that from the going forth of the Commandment to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:31868:4"/> restore and build</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>unto the</hi> Messiah, <hi>the Prince, shall be</hi> 7 <hi>Weeks, and</hi> 62 <hi>Weeks, &amp;c. And after</hi> 62 <hi>Weeks the</hi> Messiah <hi>shall be cut off, but not for himself: And the People of the Prince shall come and destroy the City, and Sanctuary, &amp;c. And he shall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Covenant with many for one Week, and in the midst of the Week he shall cause the Sacrifice and the Oblation to cease, &amp;c.</hi> Now consider this, ye <hi>Jews,</hi> and number ye this Time, the Seventy Weeks; and whether your <hi>Jerusalem</hi> was not built according to that Number; and whether the <hi>Messiah</hi> did not come; and was not he cut off after the Sixty Two Weeks? according to this Time was not he cut of? Did not you cut him off, but not for himself? And did not the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Prince come and destroy your Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and caused your Offerings to cease? Now number you this Time. And whether one which was called the <hi>Messiah</hi> did not come, according to these Years, which you would not receive? And <hi>Isaiah</hi> calls him a <hi>Prince:</hi> But when he came, he did confirm his New Covenant with many, and when he had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered up himself, he caused your Offering to cease once for all.</p>
            <p>And Dan. 12. <hi>From the Time that the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31868:5"/> daily Sacrifice shall be taken away, and the Abomination that maketh desolate set up, shall be One Thousand Two Hundred and Ninety Dayes; blessed is he that waiteth, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the Thousand Three Hundred and Five and Thirty Dayes.</hi> Now number ye this Time when it began, and when it ended; and see that you may be Partakers of this Blessing: So I desire that you would see and number the Time to the <hi>Messiah,</hi> the Prince, after the Threescore and Two Weeks; And whether ye did not cut off one in that time that was called the <hi>Messiah,</hi> who was born of a Virgin, called, the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Isaiah</hi> the Prophets, who saith, <hi>Isaiah</hi> 7. <hi>The Lord himself shall give you a Sign; behold a Virgin shall conceive, and bear a Son, and shall call his Name</hi> Immanuel. Now number you the Time in <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Messiah,</hi> the Prince, and see whether or no a Virgin had not a Child, a Son, whose Name was called <hi>Immanuel.</hi> And also the Saying of <hi>Isaiah</hi> the Prophet came upon you, <hi>Go tell this People, hearing indeed, but understand not;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 6.9, 10.</note>
               <hi>and seeing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but perceive not: Make the Heart of this People fat, and make their Ears heavy, and shut their Eyes; lest they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:31868:5"/> see with their Eyes, and hear with their Ears, and understand with their Hearts, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert and be healed.</hi> And was not this your Condition, when this Virgin had a Child, and when the <hi>Messiah</hi> came to you, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Number, which was the Sign the Lord gave you, A Virgin should have a Son, and his Name should be called <hi>Immanuel,</hi> God with us; then you would not understand this with your Hearts, nor see with your Eyes, nor hear with your Ears; but were shut up unconverted and unhealed to this day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then said I, O Lord, How long? Then said he,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 6.11, 12.</note>
               <hi>Till the City be wasted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Inhabitant, and the Houses without Man, and the Land be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly destroyed: The Lord shall remove Men far away, and there shall be a great Forsaking in the midst of the Land</hi> (Do ye not see this come upon you) <hi>But in it shall be a Tenth, and it shall return, and shall be eaten, as an Elm-Tree, or as an Oak, whose Substance is in them, when they cast their Leaves; so the Holy Seed shall be the Substance thereof.</hi> So when you have cast off your Shew, your Out-side Leaves, you may see this Tenth, and this holy Seed, the Substance of your Figures and Shadows.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:31868:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>For to us a Child is born, unto us a Son is given,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 9.6.</note>
               <hi>and the Government shall be upon his Shoulders, and his Name shall be called Wonderful, Counseller, the Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, the Everlasting Father, the Prince of Peace; of the Increase of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Peace there shall be no End, upon the Throne of</hi> David <hi>and his Kingdom, to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, and stablish it with Judgment and with Justice, from henceforth and forever: The Zeal of the Lord of Hosts will perform this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now consider this Prophecy of <hi>Isaiah;</hi> whether this Child was not born of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, this Son given, and came according to <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Number, and <hi>Isa.</hi> 11. <hi>There shall come forth a Rod out of the Stem of</hi> Jesse, <hi>and a Branch shall grow out of his Roots, and the Spirit of the Lord shall rest upon him, the Spirit of Wisdom and Ʋnderstanding, the Spirit of Counsel and Might, and the Spirit of Knowledge, and of the Fear of the Lord; and he shall make him of quick Ʋnderstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Fear of the Lord: And he shall not judge after the Sight of his Eyes, neither af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Hearing of his Ears; but with Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness shall he judge the Poor, and reprove with Equity for the Meek of the Earth; and he shall smite the Earth with the Rod of his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:31868:6"/> Mouth; and Righteousness shall be the Girdle of his Loins, and Faithfulness the Girdle of his Reins, &amp;c. And this Root of</hi> Jesse, <hi>through him the Knowledge of the Lord shall cover the Earth, as the Waters cover the Sea: And this Root of</hi> Jesse <hi>shall stand as an Ensign to the People, to it shall the</hi> Gent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les <hi>seek; and his Rest shall be Glorious.</hi> Now consider, ye <hi>Jews;</hi> is not this the <hi>Messiah</hi> spoken of, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Number, who was of the Seed of <hi>David?</hi> And now is he our Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple's Ensign; and we, that ye call <hi>Gentiles,</hi> have sought, and found; and his Rest is Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to us.</p>
            <p>And consider in <hi>Isa.</hi> 29. <hi>The Lord hath poured upon you the spirit of d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ep Slumber, and hath closed your Eye, your Prophets and your Rulers, your S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>th he covered.</hi> Was not this so, when the Virgin had a Child, the <hi>Messiah,</hi> the <hi>Immanuel,</hi> when that Sign was brought forth among you, according to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi>'s Number? And was not the Vision and the Book, and the Law and the Prophets, a sealed Book to you, which spoak of Christ to you, that when the <hi>Messiah</hi> came, you did wonder, and stagger like drunken men, but not with Wine nor Strong Drink: And though you cannot rightly read the Book of the Law and the Prophets, it being sealed up;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:31868:7"/> yet you then and now draw nigh to the Lord with your Lips, and your Mouthes do ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him, but have removed your Hearts far from him: Therefore the Lord said, <hi>Behold, I will proceed to do a Marvelous Work among this People, a Marvelous Work and a Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, For the Wisdom of the Wise Men shall perish, and the Ʋnderstanding of your Prudent Men shall be hid.</hi> And hath not this been from among you, concerning the <hi>Messiah?</hi> that Sign, That a Virgin should have a Son; and therefore he calls you in <hi>Isa.</hi> 30 <hi>Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Children;</hi> who sayes, <hi>VVo to you Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s Children, saith the Lord, that take Counsel but not of me; that cover with a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering, but not of my Spirit, that they may add sin to sin.</hi> For, had you been covered with the Spirit, you would have seen the Sign that God gave you, the Virgin having a Son, the <hi>Immanuel,</hi> who came according to <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Number: And therefore, sayes <hi>Isaiah, Saith the Lord, Write it before then in a Table, and note it in a Book, that it may be for a time to come forever and ever;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 30.1, 8.</note>
               <hi>For this is a Rebelliou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> People, Lying Children, that will not hear the Law of the Lord.</hi> So here you may see what they were in <hi>Isaiah</hi>'s dayes, and the rest of the Prophets; And you may see wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:31868:7"/> you were in <hi>Moses</hi>'s dayes, and the rest of the Judges; and what you were when the <hi>Messiah</hi> came: For did you not say to the Seers, <hi>see not;</hi> to the Prophets, <hi>prophesie not to us right Things, speak to us smooth Things, prophesie Deceit:</hi> So you may see how you were against the Prophets, and how you were all along from <hi>Moses</hi> to the <hi>Messiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Isa. 32. <hi>Behold, a King shall reign in Righteousness, &amp;c.</hi> And is not this spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the <hi>Messiah? A Man shall be as a hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Place from the Wind, and a Covert from the Tempest, as Rivers of Water in a dry Place, and as the Shadow of a great Rock in a weary Land. And the Eyes of them that see, shall not be dim; and the Ears of them that hear shall hearken:</hi> And this is wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nessed by Thousands, though you have Ears and hear not, and Eyes and see it not.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Isa.</hi> 35. Where it speaks largely of the <hi>Messiah, Who hath made the Wilderness a solitary Place, glad, and hath confirmed the weak Hands and feeble Knees, and made the fearful Heart strong, and opened the blind Eyes and deaf Ears, and made the lame Man to leap, the Tongue of the dumb to sing, and the Wilderness and the desart Water-Streams, and her parched Land to become a Pool, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:31868:8"/> thirsty Land Springs of Water:</hi> We who own the <hi>Messiah,</hi> the <hi>Immanuel,</hi> the <hi>Son</hi> of the <hi>Virgin,</hi> the Sign to you, whose Hands are weak, and Knees feeble, and Land parched thirsty, wanting the Springs that be Heavenly, and Tongues are dumb, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Messiah</hi> being come, having not the Tongue of the learned to know the Times and Seasons to be in the Fathers Hand. And <hi>Isaiah</hi> tells you of a Way, that shall be called the <hi>Way of Holiness, which shall be for those, the wayfaring M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, though Fools, shall not err therein; and the Red<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed shall walk in it, and the Ransomed of the Lord.</hi> Now are not your Eyes blind to this Way, and your Ears deaf from hearing it, this Way of Holiness, where the Unclean shall not walk over it? Mark, Is not this the Way, the <hi>Messiah?</hi> And in <hi>Isaiah</hi> 42. where he saith, <hi>Behold my Servant whom I uphold, my Elect in whom my Soul d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lighteth; I have put my Spirit upon him; he shall bring forth Judgment to the</hi> Gentiles. And this the <hi>Gentiles</hi> witness, though your Eyes are blind and cannot see this Elect, this Servant, in whom God's Soul delighteth, and hath put his Spirit upon him, who hath brought forth Judgment to the Gentiles: <hi>A bruised Reed he shall not break, and the smoaking Flax shall he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:31868:8"/> not quench; he shall bring forth Judgment to Victory; he shall not fail nor be discouraged, till he hath set Judgment in the Earth, and the Isles shall wait for his Law, &amp;c.</hi> And many have received his Law, though you <hi>Jews</hi> have had the Law, &amp; the Prophets have spoke of him that was to come, who is come; you have shut your Eyes and stopped your Ears, and have not received his Law, though you read in the Law and the Prophets of him: <hi>But I the Lord have called thee in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, and I will hold thine Hand; I will keep thee; I will give thee for a Covenant of the People, for a Light of the</hi> Gentiles: Is not this the <hi>Messiah?</hi> Is not this the <hi>Immanuel</hi> that is born of the <hi>Virgin?</hi> Yes, the <hi>Gentiles</hi> received this Light and Covenant, many Thousands, and witnesses both the Promise of God, and the Prophecies fulfilled. And further he saith, <hi>The Lord saith, that he will open the Eyes of tho blind, to bring the Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners from the Prison, &amp; them that sit in Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness out of the Prison-house: I am the Lord, that is my Name, and my Glory will I not give to another, neither my Praise to graven Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: Behold,</hi> saith he, <hi>The former Things are come to pass, and new Things do I declare; before they spring forth I tell you of them: Sing unto the Lord a new Song, and his Praise to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:31868:9"/> the Ends of the Earth, &amp;c.</hi> And you may see further; <hi>The Isles and the Inhabitants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of shall give Glory to God, and declare his Praise in the Isles.</hi> So consider now you, whose Eyes are blind, and are yet Prisoners in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and sit in Darkness, and do not behold the new Things that the Prophet declared, yea, declared them before they sprung forth, and who know not this new Song, so cannot sing it to the Lord; but who knows the <hi>Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siah,</hi> knows this new Song, knows new things: Many Islands can declare his Praise, whom the <hi>Messiah</hi> hath brought out of Darkness, the Prison-house, and opened the blind Eyes, whom the Lord hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for a Covenant of the People, for a Light to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and to be his Salvation to the Ends of the Earth; now ye know ye had the Old Covenant before. And the Lord sayes further, <hi>I will bring the blind by a Way they know not; I will lead them into Paths which they have not known; I will make Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness Light before them, and crooked Things straight; these will I do, &amp;c. Hear ye deaf, and look ye blind, that ye may see; seeing many Things, but thou observest not; opening thine Ears, but hearest not; Is not this thy Condition? Behold, thus saith the Lord, which maketh aWay in the Sea, and a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:31868:9"/> Path in the mighty Waters, &amp;c. Remember ye not the former Things, neither consider the Things of old, because I will make a new Thing, and now it shall spring forth, and ye shall not know it; the Beasts of the Field shall honour me, &amp;c.</hi> Now consider how ye have not truly minded the old Things nor the new Thing.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Isa.</hi> 50. Doth not he there speak of the <hi>Messiah,</hi> of the Son of Man, who was not rebellious: <hi>He that turned not away his Back, but said, I gave my Back to the Smi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and my Cheek to them that plucked of the Hair, and hid not my Face from Shame and Spitting?</hi> And was not this the <hi>Imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel,</hi> born of a <hi>Virgin,</hi> who came among you, according to the Number of <hi>Daniel,</hi> the <hi>Messiah?</hi> Did not you spit upon him? Did not you whip and scourge him? And did he turn his Back from you Smiters, whose Eye was blinded; <hi>But the Lord had given him the Tongue of the Learned, that he should know how to speak a Word in Season to him that is weary, &amp;c.</hi> He further saith, <hi>The Lord God will help me, therefore shall I not be confounded, therefore I have set my Face as a Flint: Behold the Lord will help me, who is he that will condemn me? lo, they all shall wax old as a Garment, and the Moth shall eat
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:31868:10"/> them up.</hi> And now ye that will not receive the <hi>Messiah,</hi> the <hi>Immanu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l,</hi> born of the <hi>Virgin,</hi> according to <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Number, that little Stone that hath dashed to Pieces the four Monarchies, become a great Mountain and filled the whole Earth; and will not this Stone fall upon your Heads, and grind you to Powder? And are not you waxed old like a Garment? and have not the Mothes eaten up many of you? And doth not <hi>Isaiah</hi> say in the 52 &amp; 53 Chapters, <hi>Behold my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant shall deal prudently; he shall be exalted &amp; be very high: As many were astonished at thee; his Visage was marred more than any Man's, and his Form more then the Sons of Men.</hi> And was not the <hi>Messiah</hi> served so with you <hi>Jews,</hi> when he came amongst you, above 1600 Years since, were not you astonished at him? Was not his Visage marred? But saith <hi>Isaiah, He shall sprinkle many Nations:</hi> This we see, though you whose Eyes are blinded cannot see; the Lord hath made bare his holy Arm in the Face of all the Nations; and all the Ends of the Earth shall see the Salvation of our God: Is not this the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel,</hi> born of a <hi>Virgin,</hi> according to <hi>Isai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi>'s Prophecy &amp; <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Number; though seeing you see not, and hearing hear not; close your Eyes and stop your Ears? But
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:31868:10"/>
               <hi>Isaiah</hi> saith, <hi>Isa.</hi> 35. <hi>Who hath believed our Report? To whom is the Arm of the Lord revealed? He shall grow up before him, as a tender Plant, and as a Root out of a dry Ground; he hath no Form nor Comliness, and when we see him, there is no Beauty, that we should desire him.</hi> And so is not this he that was born of a <hi>Virgin,</hi> the <hi>Messiah;</hi> that when he came among you, and to this Day, you could never see any Form or Comliness or Beauty, but spit upon him, and buffeted him, and put your Crown of Thorns on him; yea, sayes <hi>Isaiah, He was despised and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected of Men:</hi> And did not you despise him? did not you fulfil the Prophets Words? <hi>He was a Man of Sorrows, and acquainted with Grief, and we have hid our Faces from him; he was despised and we esteemed him not.</hi> And did you not hide your Faces from him, and despised him when he came? Did not you fulfil <hi>Isaiah</hi>'s Prophecy here concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Immanuel,</hi> who was born of a <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin?</hi> And saith <hi>Isaiah, But he was wounded for our Transgression, he was bruised for our Iniquities, the Chastizement of our Peace was upon him, and with his Stripes we are healed; all we like Sheep have gone astray, and have turned overy one to his own Way, and the Lord hath laid on him the Iniquities of us all.</hi> All you <hi>Jews</hi> every where have gone astray after
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:31868:11"/> your own VVay, till you turned to the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel,</hi> that was born of a <hi>Virgin,</hi> that was the <hi>Messiah,</hi> that came according to <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Number: <hi>He was oppressed, he was afflicted, yet he opened not his Mouth; he was brought as a Lamb to the Slaughter; and as a Sheep be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Shearers is dumb, so he opened not his Mouth.</hi> And was it not you <hi>Jews</hi> that did op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press him, and afflict him, and brought him as a Lamb to your Slaughter, as a Sheep before her Shearer is dumb; Were not you the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that did thus deal with the <hi>Messiah</hi> above 1600. Years since? <hi>He was taken from Prison &amp; Judgment, and who shall declare his Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? for he was cut off from the Land of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; for the Transgression of the People was he striken.</hi> Now consider this you <hi>Jews;</hi> was it not you that did take him from Prison and Judgment? And were not you and <hi>Pilate</hi> his Judges; who was cut off for the Transgression, and was striken for the People? And you will never come out of your Transgression, but through him, the <hi>Messiah,</hi> the <hi>Immanuel,</hi> born of the <hi>Virgin. He made his Grave with the Wicked, &amp; with the Rich in his Death, because he had done no Violence, neither was Deceit found in his Mouth: It pleas'd the Lord to bruise him, and to put him to Grief, when thou shalt make his Soul an Offering for Sin; he shall see his Seed; he shall prolong his Dayes; the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:31868:11"/> Pleasure of the Lord shall prosper in his Hand.</hi> Now here you may see you <hi>Jews,</hi> here was an Offering for Sin, who made his Soul an Offering for Sin, and ended your Offerings for Sin; this is beyond all your Offerings, and this is the Offering that pleas'd the Lord; this was he that was born of the <hi>Virgin;</hi> this was the <hi>Messiah</hi> that <hi>Daniel</hi> numbers the Years of the Time when he should come, and who came in your fore-Fathers Dayes, above 1600 Years since, and made his Soul an Offering for Sin; and he did see his Seed in the Dayes of his Disciples and Apostles, and now; and the Pleasure of the Lord did prosper in his Hand, and doth. <hi>Isaiah</hi> saith, <hi>He shall see the Travail of his Soul, and be satisfied; by his Knowledge shall my Righteous Servant justifie many; for he shall bear their Iniquity.</hi> Now you that do not believe in him, though he was an Offering for your Sin, how can you be justified? Or how can you believe in <hi>Moses</hi> or any of the Prophets that testified of him, that do not believe in him? And therefore saith the Lord, <hi>I will divide him a Portion with the great, and he shall divide the Spoil with the strong, because he hath poured out his Soul unto Death; he was numbred with the Transgressors; he bare the Sins of many, and made Intercession for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:31868:12"/> the Transgressors.</hi> Now you that do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that he bare your Sins, though he was numbred with the Transgressors; and you that do not believe that it is he that you cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, who is the Son of the <hi>Virgin,</hi> that must make Intercession for you, you neither believe in the Prophets, nor in the <hi>Messiah,</hi> nor never come to God, but by him that makes Intercession for you, and bears your Sins. Doth not <hi>Isaiah</hi> complain in Chap. 52. how his <hi>Name was blasphemed every Day?</hi> And did not you blaspheme against his Son when he came? <hi>But my People shall know my Name in that Day, that I am he that speaketh; behold, it is I.</hi> Now here was a Day to come, and happy were those of you that did behold the Day when it came; yea, the Day of the <hi>Messiah,</hi> and does behold it now. <hi>And how beautiful up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Mountains are the Feet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of him that publisheth Peace, that bringeth glad Tidings of Good, that publisheth Salvation, that saith to</hi> Sion, <hi>thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od reigneth.</hi> In <hi>Isa.</hi> 55. <hi>Ho every one that thirsteth, come ye to the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; come he that hath no Money, come, buy and eat; yea, come buy Wine and Milk with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Money and without Price, &amp;c. Incline your Ears, and come to me; hear, and your Souls shall live, and I will make an Everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:31868:12"/> Covenant with you, the sure Mercies of</hi> David: <hi>Behold I have given him, a Witness to the People, a Leader and Commander to the People: Behold thou shalt call a Nation thou knowest not; Nations that know not thee shall run to thee, because of the Lord thy God.</hi> Now mark ye <hi>Jews;</hi> this Everlasting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant which God would make; you had the first Covenant that spoke of this VVit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness which God gives, and this Leader, and this Commander to the People, that should call a Nation, and Nations should run unto him; is not this the <hi>Messiah</hi> and the <hi>Imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel,</hi> that was born of a <hi>Virgin,</hi> according to <hi>Isaiah</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Prophecy; whom you hid your Faces from, were ashamed of, and spit upon. And in <hi>Isaiah</hi> 62. <hi>The</hi> Gentiles <hi>shall see the Righteousness, and all Kings thy Glory, and thou shalt be called by a new Name which the Month of the Lord shall name.</hi> And is not this Brightness, and Salvation, and this Righteousness, and Glory, that the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> and all Kings shall see, and this new Name which the Lord shall name; is not this the <hi>Messiah,</hi> the Prince? <hi>And thou shalt be a Crown of Glory in the Hand of the Lord, a royal Diadem in the Hand of thy God.</hi> And in the 65th Chapter <hi>Isaiah</hi> saith, <hi>The Lord saith, I was sought of them that asked not for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:31868:13"/> me, I was found of them that sought me not.</hi> And were not these the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which the Messiah was promised to, who have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him; many have received him? So the Lord saith; <hi>Behold me, behold me, to a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that was not called by my Name:</hi> But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenring you <hi>Jews</hi> he saith, <hi>I have spred out my Hands all the Day to a rebellious People, which walked in a Way that was not good, after their own Thoughts, a People that provoaked me to Anger continually to my Face, &amp;c.</hi> So you may read your Rebellion, how you provoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, from <hi>Moses</hi> through all the Prophets, till you come to the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ssiah, whom you spit at: And see how other Nations have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Messiah, and run after him; and so when you call, the Lord shall not answer, because that you reject his Son. And doth not <hi>Jeremy</hi> say, <hi>As a Cage was full of Birds, so were your Houses full of Deceit; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore repent and turn.</hi> And in <hi>Jeremy</hi> 31. <hi>Behold the Dayes come, saith the Lord, that I will make a new Covenant with the House of</hi> Israel <hi>and with the House of</hi> Judah; <hi>not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Covenant that I made with their Fathers, in the Day that I took them by the Hand, to bring them out of the Land of</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, <hi>which my Covenant they broke though I was a Husband to them, saith the Lord,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:31868:13"/> Here you (may see you forsook your Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band) that broke the Covenant. But here is a new Covenant, which is not according to the old: And now this new Covenant you have not received, and will not receive: For as he said, <hi>I will give him for a Covenant,</hi> that is the Messiah, he that was born of a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin. <hi>But this is the Covenant that I will make with the House of</hi> Israel <hi>after those Dayes.</hi> Now here are the Dayes of the old Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; here are the Dayes of the new, <hi>Saith the Lord, I will put my Laws in their Hearts, and write them in your inward Parts; and I will be their God, and they shall be my People; and they shall not teach every Man their Neighbour, and every Man his Brother, saying, Know the Lord, for they shall all know me from the least of them to the greatest of them, saith the Lord.</hi> And it is said in <hi>Isa.</hi> 54. <hi>All thy Children shall be taught of the Lord, &amp; great shall be the Peace of thy Children; in Righteousness shalt thou be established, &amp;c.</hi> So consider, you will never own the new Covenant, till you own the <hi>Messiah</hi> is come. In the 32. of <hi>Jeremy, I will make an Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Covenant with them, that I will not turn away from them, to do them good; but I will put my Fear in their Hearts, that they shall not depart from me:</hi> So now this is the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:31868:14"/> new Covenant which you must all receive, if you come to be God's People, and he your God; and to have the one Heart and the one Way, it must be in this Everlasting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
            <p>And you that crucifie the Messiah, did not God raise him up the third Day, that he might live in his Sight? So if ever you live to God, it is through him; For in <hi>Hosea</hi> 6. <hi>After two Dayes he will revive us; in the third Day he will raise us up, and we shall live in his Sight.</hi> And was not this a Prophecy of the Resurrection of the Messiah, whom you crucified? <hi>For the Lord desired Mercy of you and not Sacrifice, and the Knowledge of God rather then burnt Offerings, but you like Men, have transgressed the Covenant, and dealt treacherously against me, saith the Lord. Micah</hi> saith in the 4th <hi>Chapter, That in the last Dayes the Mountain of the Lord's house shall be established on the Top of the Mountains; and shall be exalted above the hills, and People shall flow unto it, and many Nations shall come and say, Come and let us go up to the Mountain of the house of the Lord, to the house of the God of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and he will teach us of his Wayes, and we shall walk in his Paths, &amp;c.</hi> Now ye <hi>Jews;</hi> consider this; is not this the new Covenant, where many
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:31868:14"/> Nations now come to be taught of God? and God doth teach them his Wayes to walk in; and he shall judge among the People, and judge many strong Nations, &amp;c. And is not this in the Dayes of the Messiah, which many witness.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Micah</hi> 5. <hi>But thou</hi> Bethlehem E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phratah, <hi>though thou be little among the Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of</hi> Judah, <hi>yet out of thee shall come forth to me, that is to be a Ruler in</hi> Israel, <hi>whose Goings forth have been from of Old, from Everlasting; and he shall stand and feed in the strength of the Lord, in the Majesty of the name of the Lord his God; for now he shall be great to the Ends of the Earth, &amp;c.</hi> And now ye <hi>Jews,</hi> was not here that the Messiah should come out of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> of <hi>Judah,</hi> to be a Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler; &amp; this is the Son that the Virgin bare, the <hi>Immanuel:</hi> And therefore it is said, <hi>I will give t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em up, ll the time that she that travels hath brought forth;</hi> &amp; when she <hi>Mary,</hi> the Virgin, had brought forth, who was advised by the Angel what to call her Son, to wit, Jesus; all <hi>Jerusalem</hi> was on an Uproar; look back you <hi>Jews:</hi> And did not <hi>Herod</hi> your King, who was troubled also; did he not gather all the chief Priests; and Scribes of the People, and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manded of them where the Messiah should be born? and they said to him, In <hi>Bethlehem
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:31868:15"/> Judah;</hi> so saith the Prophet, <hi>Mic.</hi> 5. <hi>For thou</hi> Bethlehem <hi>in the Land of</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, <hi>though thou be the least among the Thousands of</hi> Judah, <hi>yet out of thee shall come forth to me, that is to be a Ruler in</hi> Israel, <hi>whose Goings forth have been from of Old, from Everlasting: And he shall stand and feed in the Strength of the Lord, in the Majesty of the Name of the Lord his God; for now he shall be great to the Ends of the Earth, &amp;c.</hi> And now ye <hi>Jews,</hi> was not here, that the Messiah should come out of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> of <hi>Judah,</hi> to be a Ruler? and this is the Son that the Virgin bare, the <hi>Immanuel.</hi> And therefore it is he saith, <hi>He will give them up, untill the Time that she which travaileth hath brought forth:</hi> And when she, even the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, had brought forth, who was advised by the Angel what to call her Son, to wit, Jesus, all <hi>Jerusalem</hi> was on an Uproar; look back ye <hi>Jews:</hi> And did not <hi>Herod</hi> your King, who was troubled also, did not he gather all the chief Priests and Scribes of the People, and demanded of them where the Messi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah should be born; and they said to him, in <hi>Bethlehem Judah;</hi> so saith the Prophet, <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah</hi> 5. <hi>For thou</hi> Bethlehem <hi>in the Land of</hi> Judah, <hi>though thou be the least among the Thousands of</hi> Judah, <hi>yet out of thee shall come
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:31868:15"/> forth to me, that is to be a Ruler in</hi> Israel And so did not <hi>Herod</hi> in his Envy seek the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of this Messiah? And therefore not killing him, that it might be fulfilled which was spoken by <hi>Jeremy</hi> the Prophet, <hi>Ch.</hi> 31. when he had killed the Children from such an Age: <hi>Thus saith the Lord, A Voice was heard in</hi> Ramah, <hi>Lamentation and bitter Weeping;</hi> Rachel <hi>weeping for her Children, &amp; would not be comforted, because they were not.</hi> And the Messiah was carri'd down into <hi>Egypt,</hi> when <hi>Herod</hi> sought his Life, that it might be fulfilled which was spoken of him; <hi>Out of</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt <hi>have I call'd my Son,</hi> Hos. 11. So here you may see it is clear, how the Messiah was born in <hi>Bethlehem;</hi> now number you, according to the Prophecy: A Virgin had a Child, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his Name <hi>Immanuel;</hi> whether was he not born in <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> according to <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Number, and the Prophets Prophecy of him?</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Psal.</hi> 2. <hi>Why do the</hi> Heathen <hi>rage, and the People imagine a vain Thing; the Kings of the Earth set themselves, and the Rulers take Counsel together against the Lord, and against his Anointed.</hi> Is not this the Messiah? &amp; was not this fulfilled in you when he came? &amp; to this Day do not ye rage against him? But further he saith in the same <hi>Psalm, Thou art my Son, this Day have I begotten
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:31868:16"/> thee, therefore kiss this Son, lest he be angry, and ye perish from the Way, when his Wrath is kindled but a little; blessed are all they that trust in him, in this Son.</hi> And again he saith, in <hi>Psalm.</hi> 16. <hi>I have set the Lord alwayes before me, because he is at my right Hand, and I shall not be moved; and therefore my Heart is glad, and my Glory rejoyceth: my Flesh al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so shall rest in Hope; for thou wilt not leave my Soul in Hell, neither wilt thou suffer thy Holy One to see Corruption.</hi> Now is not this the Messiah, the <hi>Immanuel,</hi> born of the Virgin, that Sign that God gave to you, who wrought Signs and Miracles among you, though you despised, and wondred at, and crucified, and buried, who rose the third Day, and did not see Corruption; but God raised him up, who is at his right Hand: And did not your Priests give the Souldiers large Money, that watched his Sepulchre where he was laid, to say, that the Disciples stole him away by Night? And did not you crucifie him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two Thieves? And was not he na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med among Transgressors? Read <hi>Isaiah</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: And when ye crucified him, did not ye <hi>Jews</hi> say, <hi>He trusted in the Lord, that he would deliver him; let him deliver him, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he loveth him,</hi> Psalm. 22. And in <hi>Wisd.</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Did not you fulfil the Sayings there: <hi>He
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:31868:16"/> maketh his Boast that God is his Father; let us see if his Words be true; let us prove what will happen in the End of him; for if the just Man be the Son of God, he will help him and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him from the Hand of his Enemy; let us condemn him with a shameful Death.</hi> And this you did, when ye crucified the Messiah: As it is said in <hi>Psalm</hi> 31. <hi>Into thy Hand I commit my Spirit, &amp;c.</hi> And in <hi>Psalm</hi> 34. <hi>He keepeth all my Bones, not one of them is broken:</hi> So this was fulfilled upon the Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siah, not a Bone of him was broken; though ye broke the Thieves Legs, yet had not Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to break his Bones: Therefore it is said in <hi>Psal.</hi> 40. <hi>Sacrifice and Offerings thou didst not desire; mine Ears hast thou opened; Burnt-Offerings and Sin-Offerings hast thou not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired</hi> (Mark ye <hi>Jews) then said I, lo, I come; in the Volumn of thy Book it is written of me, I delight to do thy Will, O my God; yea, thy Law is within my Heart.</hi> Is not this the Messiah, the Immanuel, whom ye crucified? In the Volumn of the Law and Prophets it was written of him; you must never expect to see any other. And so in <hi>Isaiah</hi> 63. <hi>I have trodden the Win<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-Press a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alone.</hi> So if you <hi>Jews</hi> did mind the 6th of <hi>Hos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a; The Lord desired Mercy and not Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, the Knowledge of God more then
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:31868:17"/> Burnt-Offerings.</hi> And when this Sign was brought forth among you, that this Virgin had a Child, <hi>Immanuel; Then did the Lord confirm his Covenant with an Oath, which he made with</hi> Abraham, Isaac <hi>and</hi> Jacob, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the</hi> Messiah, Psal. 105. And <hi>Psal.</hi> 110. <hi>The Lord said to my Lord, sit thou on my right Hand, till I make thine Enemies thy Footstool, &amp;c. The Lord hath sworn and will not repent; thou art a Priest forever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Order of</hi> Melchizedeck: And is not this the <hi>Messiah,</hi> the <hi>Immanuel,</hi> which came among you, according to <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Number? And in <hi>Psalm.</hi> 118. <hi>The Stone which the Builders refused is become the head Stone of the Corner; this is the Lord's doing, and it is marvelous in our Eyes.</hi> And is not this <hi>the Immanuel,</hi> which was born of a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, the Messiah, which came to you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Prophecy above 1600 Years ago, whom you <hi>Jews,</hi> that were the pretended Builders of People up to Heaven, refused and rejected this Corner-Stone? and therefore were not your Cities, your Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses &amp; Religion all thrown down by the Storm of <hi>Titus,</hi> and you blown over all Nations? And in <hi>Psalm.</hi> 132. <hi>For thy Servant</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid<hi>'s sake, turn not away the Face of thine Anointed: The Lord hath sworn in Truth to</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:31868:17"/> David, <hi>he will not turn from it, of the Fruit of thy Body will I set upon thy Throne, there will I make the Horn of</hi> David <hi>to bud; I have ordained a Light for mine Anointed.</hi> Now you <hi>Jews,</hi> doth not this speak of the Messiah? and was not he to come of the Seed of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> as God had promised and sworn? And see in <hi>Daniel,</hi> if he did not come according to the Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi>'s Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. And in <hi>Isaiah</hi> 8. <hi>He shall be for a Sanctuary, for a Stone of stumbling, for a Rock of Offence to both the houses of</hi> Israel, <hi>for a Gin, for a Snare to the Inhabitants of</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>salem; <hi>and many among them shall stumble and fall, and be broken, and be snared, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; bind up the Testimony, seal the Law among my Disciples.</hi> Is not this spoken of that the Messiah? And were not you the People stumbled and fell? Was not he a Rock of Offence for you both ye Houses of <hi>Israel?</hi> He was no Sanctuary to you that stuck in your outward Sanctuary. And did not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Thousands among you <hi>Jews</hi> wait for the Messiah, and received him at that Time when he came? And many of his Disciples which believed on him and received him, among whom the Law and Testimony was bound up and sealed among them; and you stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at him, this Stone; Is not this the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:31868:18"/> Stone that <hi>Daniel</hi> interpreted in <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezar</hi>'s Dream, that should dash to Pieces the four Monarchies, and become a great Mountain, and fill the whole Earth, which should set up a Kingdom that should never have an End; and your Kingdoms had an End, and is ended. Was not he a Priest for ever after the Order of <hi>Melchizedeck?</hi> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Priests dyed, and had an End; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ough you crucified him, yet he is risen, and is at the right Hand of God, and is a Priest forever, who ever liveth to save to the utmost, and makes Intercession, who is not after the Order of <hi>Aaron,</hi> but after the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Melchizedeck.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is said of the Redeemer, Isa. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>He shall put on Righteousness as a Breast-Plate, and an Helmet of Salvation upon his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ead; and he shall put on the Garment of Vengeance for Cloathing; and he was clod with Zeal as a Cloak: and the Redeemer shall come to</hi> Zion, <hi>and to them that turn from Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression in</hi> Jacob, <hi>saith the Lord. As for me, this is my Covenant, saith the Lord, My Spirit that is upon thee, and my Words that I have put in thy Mouth, shall not d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>part out of the Mouth of thy Seed, nor out of the Mouth of thy Seed's Seed, saith the Lord, from henceforth and forever.</hi> So many did wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:31868:18"/> this fulfilled when the <hi>Messiah</hi> came, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Prophets, to you <hi>Jews:</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny received him; but you <hi>Jews,</hi> that turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not from your Transgressions (but lived in your Blindness) stumbled, and Darkness covered you, gross Darkness!</p>
            <p>But in <hi>Isa.</hi> 60. <hi>The</hi> Gentiles <hi>shall come to his Light.</hi> This Prophecy many of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> witness, that are come to his Light: For it is said, <hi>A Little One shall become a Thousand, a Small One a Strong Nation; I the Lord will hasten it in his time.</hi> Is not this the Branch of the Lord's own planting? And many are Witnesses of it, though you cannot see it this Day, and see his Kingdom. <hi>The Gates are opon Day and Night, that men may bring to thee the Force of the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>and that their Kings may be brought;</hi> though you blind <hi>Jews</hi> cannot see it: <hi>And they shall call thee the City of the Lord, the Zeal of the Holy One of</hi> Israel, <hi>he who is the Joy of many Generations. Thou shalt suck the Milk of the</hi> Gentiles; signifying that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> have a Breast.</p>
            <p>And in Isa. 61. <hi>The Spirit of the Lord is upon me; he hath anointed me to preach Good Tidings to the Meek; he hath sent me to bind up the Broken Heart, to proclaim Liberty to the Captives, and the opening of the Prison
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:31868:19"/> to them that are bound, &amp;c.</hi> And was not this fulfilled when he came, according to <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Prophecy? And did not he open the Book among your People, and told you, it was fulfilled, in one of your Synagogues at <hi>Nazareth,</hi> when one of you delivered him the Book of <hi>Isaiah?</hi> then you did won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at him, at the Gracious Words for a time; but you were quickly changed, and thrust him out of your City, to throw him down the Brow of your Hill.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Isaiah</hi> 66. where he saith, <hi>Heaven is my Throne, Earth is my Foot-Stool; where is the House that ye will build to me? where is the Place of my Rest?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And you that look so much at your Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Temple, did not the <hi>Messiah</hi> tell you, <hi>That it should be thrown down, and not one Stone left upon another in that Generation?</hi> And was it not done by <hi>Titus?</hi> and have you built it since?</p>
            <p>And doth not the Lord say, <hi>All these things have my Hands made, and all these things have been, saith the Lord; but to this man will I look, even to him that is poor, and of a Contrite Spirit, and trembleth at my Word,</hi> And in <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 31. <hi>This is the Covenant that I will make with the House of</hi> Israel, <hi>After those dayes, saith the Lord, I will put
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:31868:19"/> my Law in their inward Parts, and write them in their Hearts; and I will be their God, and they shall be my People; they shall teach no more every man his Neighbour, and every man his Brother, saying, Know the Lord; for they shall all know me, from the Greatest to the Least of them, saith the Lord; for I will forgive their Iniquities, and their Sins I will remember no more.</hi> And now mark; This is a Covenant after these dayes: You had the Old Covenant before, where ye were teaching one another his Brother, &amp;c. and where ye were writing the Laws, the Laws written in Tables of Stone; but here the Lord is the Writer, in the New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to write them in your Hearts: So, as you receive this Covenant, and come into this Covenant, your Sins and Iniquities will be forgiven, and be remembred no more. So God saith, <hi>I will give him for a Covenant,</hi> meaning his <hi>Messiah,</hi> he that is born of a Virgin, that you crucified: If you receive not him, do you think your Sins and Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties will not be remembred?</p>
            <p>And how can you or dare you take the Title to be called, <hi>God's People?</hi> For, <hi>They shall be my People, and I will be the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r God that come into this Covenant, which God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:31868:20"/> which is the New Covenant;</hi> for you had the Old before.</p>
            <p>Read <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. <hi>And I will give them one Heart.</hi> Ezek. 11. <hi>And I will put a new Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit within them; I will take away the Stony Heart out of their Flesh, and I will give them a Heart of Flesh.</hi> Now they that believed in the <hi>Messiah,</hi> are Witnesses of this; yea, those <hi>Jews</hi> that believed in him above One Thousand Six Hundred Years since, witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed this New Spirit, this one Heart, this Heart of Flesh, and this New Covenant; but you that did not, and do not believe, witness the Stony Heart and Old Spirit, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring about the Old Covenant and stumbling at the New; and are Breakers of the Old too, and Despisers of the New Covenant, and of God's Oath concerning it.</p>
            <p>And again, The Lord saith in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. <hi>Cast away from you all your Transgressions, whereby ye have transgressed, and make you a New Heart and a New Spirit; For why will ye dye, ye House of</hi> Israel? <hi>For I have no Pleasure in the Death of him that dyeth, saith the Lord, wherefore return, and live ye.</hi> Now here you <hi>Jews</hi> may see, that without turning from your Transgression you do not live, neither have you a new Heart, nor a new
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:31868:20"/> Spirit, &amp; not turning you dye. And the Lord saith, He hath no Pleasure in it, and in your Death, Ezek. 34. <hi>I will set up One Shepherd, saith the Lord, and he shall feed them, and he shall be your Shepherd: I the Lord will be your God, and my Servant</hi> David <hi>a Prince; and I will make with them a Covenant of Peace.</hi> And is not this One Shepherd, that the Lord will set up, the <hi>Immanuel,</hi> born of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, which came according to the Prophecy of <hi>Isaiah,</hi> and according to <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber? And when he was come, did not he say, That he <hi>was the True Shepherd, that laid down his Life for his Sheep?</hi> And is not he the Covenant of Peace spoken of by <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiel?</hi> Did not he come of the Seed of <hi>David?</hi> And did not, and do not you yet reject this Shepherd, this Feeder, and his Covenant of Peace, and this Seed of <hi>David?</hi> And therefore, what Evil Seed are ye run into?</p>
            <p>And <hi>Ezekiel</hi> in the 36th Chapter, <hi>Saith the Lord, I will sprinkle clean Water upon you, and ye shall be clean, &amp;c. And I will give you a New Heart, and a New Spirit I will put within you, and take away your Stony Heart, &amp;c. And I will open your Graves, and I will bring you out of your Graves, and put my Spirit in you. Moreover, I will make
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:31868:21"/> a Covenant of Peace with you, which shall be an Everlasting Covenant, and I will set my Sanctuary in the midst of them for evermore; my Tabernacle also shall be with them, and I will be their God, and they shall be my Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and</hi> David <hi>shall be their Prince forever.</hi> This you must know was the <hi>Messiah,</hi> the Seed of <hi>David;</hi> for <hi>David</hi> was dead long before: But you must be come out of your Graves of Sin and Wickedness, and your own Traditions, and come out of the Old Covenant, and come into the New; if ye know this Seed of <hi>David,</hi> the <hi>Messiah,</hi> you must come out of the Seed of Transgression and Rebellion, Blindness and Darkness, and see your selves in the Graves, and your Bones scattered, before you be gathered to this One Shepherd, that God sets over his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the New Covenant. Read the 36th &amp; 37th of <hi>Ezekiel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Michah</hi> 4. <hi>In the last dayes it shall come to pass, that the Mountain of the House of the Lord shall be stablished upon the tops of the Mountains, and it shall be exalted above the Hills; and many Nations shall say, Come, and let us go up to the Mountain of the Lord, to the House of the God of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and he will teach us of his Wayes, and we shall walk in his Pathes; and the Kingdom shall
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:31868:21"/> come to the Daughter of</hi> Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>usalem. Now you that did not receive the Messiah have lost these Last Dayes of God's Teaching, and neglecting these last days of God's Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, which many are come to, and can say, <hi>He doth teach them of his VVays, and they walk in his Pathes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this Kingdom that should come to the Daughter of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> many in the time when the <hi>Messiah</hi> came did both receive him as King, and were Heirs of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and so there are many at this day: But you that rejected the <hi>Messiah,</hi> rejected both King and Kingdom, and God's Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on his Mountain, <hi>Mic.</hi> 4. And so the Saying of <hi>Habbakkuk</hi> 1.5. is come upon you, <hi>Behold ye among the</hi> Heathen, <hi>and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and wonder; for I work a VVork in your dayes which ye will not believe, though it be told you;</hi> for ye would not believe <hi>Jeremy</hi> the Prophet, nor the other Prophets, nor the Son, the <hi>Messiah,</hi> the <hi>Immanuel,</hi> born of the Virgin; though they that did believe in him, the Just shall live by his Faith. So you may see in <hi>Habbakkuk</hi> 2.4. for the Vision was for an appointed time, and in the End it did speak, the Vision or the Sign, as you may read in <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Isaiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:31868:22"/>
            <p>And <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. where the Lord saith, <hi>I will pour upon the Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se of</hi> David, <hi>and upon the Inhabitants of</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>the Spirit of Grace and of Supplication, and they shall look upon him whom they have pierced, and they shall mourn for him as one mourneth for his Son, his only Son; and they shall be in Bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness for him, as one that is in B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tterness for his First-born.</hi> And now mark ye <hi>Jews,</hi> what <hi>Him</hi> is it that ye have pierced? Is it not the <hi>Immanuel,</hi> born of a Virgin, the <hi>Messiah,</hi> which came according to <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Number of Years? They that did believe in him did mourn bitterly, and were pricked in their Hearts; so you may look back above One Thousand Six Hundred Years since; they came to be the Learners of him: And you that stand still in your Blindness &amp; Hardness of Heart, and have not mourned, and do not believe in him that you have pierced, you cannot witness the Spirit of Grace and Supplication upon you yet, as they had that did look upon him that they had pierced Mal. 3. <hi>And behold, saith the Lord, I wil send my Messenger, and he shall prepare the Way before me: And the Lord whom ye seek shall suddenly com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to his Temple, &amp;c. But who shall abide the Day of his Coming? F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:31868:22"/> he shall sit as a Refiner's Fire, &amp;c.</hi> Mal. 4.5. <hi>Behold I will send you</hi> Elias <hi>the Prophet before the Coming of the Great and Terrible Day of the Lord: and he shall turn the Hearts of the Fathers to the Children, and the Hearts of the Children to the Fathers; lest I come and smite the Earth with a Curse.</hi> And when this <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias</hi> did come, did not ye do to him what ye listed? And so, did not he come before the <hi>Messiah,</hi> and prepare the VVay before him? For ye did believe that <hi>John Baptist</hi> was a <hi>Prophet,</hi> some of you; and some said, that he was a <hi>Devil:</hi> For did not <hi>Isaiah</hi> Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie of him in the 40th Chapter, and the 3d Verse? <hi>The Voice of one crying in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, Prepare the VVay of the Lord, make his Pathes streight; Every Vall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y shall be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and every Mountain and Hill shall be brought low, and the Crooked shall be made streight, and the Rough VVayes smooth, and all Flesh shall see the Salvation of God.</hi> Now was not this <hi>John,</hi> the Son of <hi>Zachariah,</hi> that <hi>Isaiah</hi> prophesied of? Did not <hi>John</hi> here fulfil <hi>Isaiah</hi>'s Prophecy, the Fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Christ? So if you will neither believe the Prophet <hi>Isaiah,</hi> nor <hi>John</hi> the Prophet, nor the <hi>Messiah,</hi> the <hi>Immanuel,</hi> born of a Virgin, which came according to the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Angel to <hi>Daniel,</hi> but your
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:31868:23"/> Crooked Pathes are not made streight, nor your Rough Spirit and Mind is not made smooth, and your Mountain of Sin is not brought low; and therefore how were ye like to see the Salvation of God when he came; but you hid your Faces from him, and so fulfilled <hi>Isaiah</hi>'s Prophecy. But when God had given you a Temple, when the <hi>Messi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> came, he found in the Temple such as sold Oxen, Sheep and Doves, and Money-Changers sitting there, which should have been a House of Prayer; And so was not here the <hi>Psalm</hi> fulfilled, <hi>Psal.</hi> 69.9. <hi>The Zeal of my Father's House hath eaten me up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Zach. 9.9. <hi>Rejoyce greatly, O Daughter of</hi> Zion, <hi>shout O Daughter of</hi> Jerusalem; <hi>Behold, thy King cometh to thee; he is Just, and having Salvation; Lowly, and riding upon an Ass, upon a Colt, the Foal of an Ass.</hi> Now consider, did not he come so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> this <hi>Immanuel,</hi> this <hi>Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siah?</hi> And did not many of your Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Rejoyce, and cryed <hi>Hosanna?</hi> But your Priests that were blind, and the rest of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pharisees</hi> and <hi>Jews</hi> Railed at him, and Blasphemed against him. <hi>But He is</hi> He <hi>that speaks Peace to the</hi> Heathen,<note place="margin">Zach. 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0, 11.</note>
               <hi>and his Dominion is from Sea to Sea, and from the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:31868:23"/> River to the Ends of the Earth. And as for thee also in the Blood of thy Covenant, I have sent forth thy Prisoners out of the Pit wherein is no Water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in Zach. 11.12, 13. <hi>And I said to them, If ye think good, give me my Price; if not, forbear: so ye weighed to my Price Thirty Pieces of Silver; and the Lord said to me, Cast it to the Potter, a goodly Price that I was prized at by them; so I cast them to the Potter in the House of the Lord.</hi> And did not your High Priest give <hi>Judas</hi> Thirty Pieces of Silver for to betray the <hi>Messiah?</hi> So was not this Prophecy fulfilled upon you, as <hi>David</hi> sayes in <hi>Psal.</hi> 41.9. <hi>Yea, my own familiar Friend, that did eat of my Bread, hath lifted up his Heel against me:</hi> was not this fulfilled in your <hi>Judas?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Also <hi>David</hi> saith in <hi>Psal</hi> 69.21, 22, 23. <hi>They gave me Gaul for my Meat, in my Thirst they gave me Vinegar to drink: Let their Table become a Snare before them, and their Posterity a Ruin: Let their Eyes be darkened, that they see not; make their Joynts continually shake; let their Habitation be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solate, and let none dwell in their Tents.</hi> Now consider when the <hi>Messiah</hi> was come, and when ye crucified him, did not ye give him Vinegar and Gaul to drink? and was not
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:31868:24"/> your Table, and is it not a Snare and a Trap, and your Eyes blinded, and your Habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons desolate, which ye had at Jerusalem in <hi>David</hi>'s Time? So how can you say, that that was not the Messiah in all these Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies you have so fulfilled upon the Messiah? And in <hi>Psalm</hi> 109 8. &amp;c. <hi>Let his Dayes be saw; let another take his Office:</hi> This was spoken of <hi>Judas,</hi> to whom your Chief Priests gave the thirty Peices of Silver, that he might betray the Messiah into your Hands: <hi>Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> another take his Office;</hi> so another Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Jesus, the Messiah, the Lord, was put in his Room: So this was fulfilled, <hi>Psalm</hi> 22.16, 17. <hi>For Dogs have compassed me; the Assembly of the wicked have enclosed me; they pierced my Hands and my Feet; they parted my Garments among them, and cast Lots upon my Vesture.</hi> And now ye <hi>Jews,</hi> did not ye often assemble together to crucifie him? And when you did crucifie him, did not you pierce his Hands and Feet? And did not you part his Garments among you, the Messiah, when they crucified him? And did not your Souldiers cast Lots upon his Vesture? And doth not <hi>Moses</hi> say in the 18th of <hi>Deuteronomy, The Lord thy God will raise up a Prophet in the midst of thee, of thy Brethren, like to me, to him shall ye hearken:</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:31868:24"/> And further he saith, <hi>I will raise them up a Prophet of their Brethren, like to thee, and I will put my Words in his Mouth, and he shall speak to them all that I shall command him; and it shall come to pass, that whosoever shall not hearken to my Words that he shall speak in my Name, I will require it of him.</hi> Now this Prophet, like to <hi>Moses,</hi> was the Messi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah, which was the Sign born of a Virgin, according to the the Prophecy of <hi>Is iah:</hi> And <hi>Daniel</hi> numbred the Years to the Messi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah, and the Time that he should be cut off, should make his Soul a Sacrifice, according to the Prophet: <hi>And there rose not a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet since in</hi> Israel, <hi>like to</hi> Moses, <hi>whom the Lord knew Face to Face,</hi> as it is said in <hi>Deut.</hi> 34. So this Prophet that God has raised up, like <hi>Moses,</hi> whom the People should hear in all Things, was not <hi>Joshuah,</hi> but the Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siah, whom you would not, nor did not hear; and so not hearing him, you hear not the Prophets. And God said to <hi>Abraham, In thy Seed shall all the Families of the Earth be blessed,</hi> Gen. 12. And <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. <hi>All the Nations of the Earth shall be blessed in Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s <hi>Seed; and I know he will command his Children and his Houshold after him, and they shall keep the Way of the Lord to do Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce and Judgment.</hi> And in <hi>Gen.</hi> 22. <hi>The
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:31868:25"/> Lord said to</hi> Abraham, <hi>By my self have I sworn, because thou hast done this Thing, and hast not withheld thine only Son; that in blessing I will bless thee, &amp; in multiplying I will multiply thee as the Stars of Heaven, &amp; in thy Seed shall all Nations of the Earth be blessed.</hi> And so was not <hi>Abram</hi>'s offering up his only Son <hi>Isaac</hi> a Type of the Messiah's making his Soul an Offering, the Messiah's making his Soul a Sacrifice for the Sins of men, who according to the Flesh was of the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who was the Son of God, a Sign and Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to you to this Day, that a Virgin should have a Child? And did not <hi>Jacob</hi> say on his Death-Bed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10, 11. when he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his Sons together, he said to <hi>Judah,</hi> when he prophesied to them all; Judah, <hi>thou art he whom thy Brethren shall praise; thy Hand shall be on the Neck of thine Enemies; thy Father's Children shall bow down before thee; the Scepter shall not depart from</hi> Judah, <hi>nor a Law-Giver from between his Feet till Shilo come, and unto him shall the Gathering be of the People?</hi> And now consider; did not the Scepter continue in <hi>Judah</hi> till Shilo the Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siah came? But is not the Scepter departed from <hi>Judah</hi> above 1600. Years since, after you had crucified the Messiah? And are not your Walls and City of <hi>Jerusalem</hi> broken
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:31868:25"/> down, trodden under Foot, and you scattered over all Nations? And so is not your Scepter gone? So consider these Things, how long it is since you lost your Scepter: It should not depart till Shilo came; and he came, and is come, and you would not hearken to him, being a stif-necked People.</p>
            <p>Is it not clear that the Messiah came of the Seed of <hi>David</hi> and of <hi>Abraham,</hi> according to the Prophets, who was born of a Virgin, though you were rebellious, as you may see from <hi>Moses</hi> through the Prophets to the Messiah; though some of you in all Ages did believe, yet for the Generality of you, what a stiff-necked People you were, that your <hi>Eyes were blinded, your Table was made a Snare, and you stuck in the Old Covenant and opposed the New:</hi> And were not your Backs often therefore bowed down; yea, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all the Governments of the World now: And so <hi>Isaiah</hi>'s Prophecy is come upon you, saying, <hi>Go tell this People,</hi> Isa. 6.9. <hi>hearing ye hear not, seeing ye see not, and do not perceive for the Heart of this People is waxed gross, and their Ears are dull of Hearing; and their Eyes have they closed, lest they should see with their Eyes, and hear with their Ears, and understand with their Hearts, and should be converted, and I should heal them:</hi> This is
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:31868:26"/> a sad Condition; you would not receive the Immanuel, born of a Virgin; and therefore was not the Salvation sent to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> might glorifie God for his Mercy through the Messiah? <hi>For this Cause I will confess thee among the</hi> Gentiles,<note place="margin">Psal. 18.49.</note>
               <hi>and sing to thy Name.</hi> And again he saith, <hi>Rejoyce ye</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles <hi>with his People.</hi> Now those <hi>Jews</hi> that were the Believers in the Messiah the <hi>Gentiles</hi> can rejoyce withal. And <hi>Psal.</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Praise the Lord ye</hi> Gentiles, <hi>and laud him all ye People.</hi> And again <hi>Isaiah</hi> saith, <hi>There shall be a Root of</hi> Jesse, <hi>and he shall rise to reign over the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>in him the</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles <hi>shall trust.</hi> Now this is the Messiah that was born of a Virgin, whom ye crucified, who is risen, in whom the <hi>Gentiles</hi> rejoyce and trust, who is their Salvation; read <hi>Isa.</hi> 11, 10. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o it was said before to you; <hi>Like to me</hi> (saith <hi>Moses) will God raise up a Prophet of your Brethren, him shall ye hear in all Things, whatsoever he shall say to you; and that Soul that will not hear this Prophet shall be destroyed from among the People.</hi> So was not the Messiah of the Seed of <hi>David</hi> and of <hi>Abraham;</hi> and when God had raised him up, and brought him forth, you would not hear him, neither before ye crucified
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:31868:26"/> him, nor now when he is risen, who came according to <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Prophecy: And so in this you neither hear God, nor <hi>Moses,</hi> nor the Prophets, nor the Angel, nor the Son the Messiah; and so in this you neither keep the Law, nor the Prophets, nor the Old Covenant, nor the New, though you often spoak fair with your Mouths, but your Hearts were far off.</p>
            <p>Is not that come to pass which the Messiah spoke to you, <hi>That you should be led away Captive, and many should fall by the Edge of the Sword, and</hi> Jerusalem <hi>should be compassed with Armies, and you should be led Captive into all Nations, and</hi> Jerusalem <hi>shall be trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den down</hi> (read in <hi>Daniel</hi> the 9th) And was not <hi>Jerusalem</hi> built and standing till Messiah, the Prince? And when he came, was not he cut off? And after did not <hi>Titus</hi> the Prince of the People come to destroy your City and Sanctuary; therefore was not this the true Messiah, the Immanuel, born of a Virgin, and the Prophet that you should hear in all Things; and they that did hear him, and do hear him. do witness the Prophecy of <hi>Joel</hi> to be fulfilled; <hi>The Lord is pouring out of his Spirit upon all Flesh, his Sons, his Daughters, his Old Men, his Young Men, Servants, Handmaids:</hi> These are the Dayes
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:31868:27"/> of the Messiah; for he sayes, <hi>In those Dayes I will pour out my Spirit:</hi> So by the Spirit of God they can praise God, Sons, Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Old Men, Young Men, Servants, Handmaids through the Messiah, the Imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel, who was born of a Virgin, whom you crucified, and is risen, and is at the right Hand of God, who is our Prophet, and Shepherd, and Covenant of Peace, through him we can praise God, <hi>Hallelujah</hi> for ever and ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And you that despise him despise your Salvation, and lye under the Judgment of the Prophets and the Son, as you may see in the Scriptures; And therefore it is Time for you to repent, and turn to him.</p>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>A Postscript.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>NOt a Bone of the Pascal-Lamb shall be broken,</hi> Num. 9.12. And was not this a Type of the Pascal-Lamb, the <hi>Messiah,</hi> of whom you had not Power to break a Bone, although
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:31868:27"/> you broak the Bones of the Two Thieves that were crucified on each side of him?</p>
               <p>And in <hi>Deut.</hi> 8. there you may see how the Lord in the Wilderness hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled your Fathers to reprove them, and to know what was in their hearts, whether they would keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments or no; Therefore he humbled them, and made them to Hunger, and fed them with <hi>Manna,</hi> which they knew not, neither did the Fathers know it, that he might teach them, That Man liveth not by Bread only, but by every Word that proceedeth out of the Mouth of the Lord doth a Man live; yet how soon did your Fore Fathers for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the Lord, and lusted after <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi>'s Flesh pots, as ye may read in the Books of <hi>Moses,</hi> how your Fore-Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers murmured against the Lord, and turned against him, and his Prophets, and his Son, the <hi>Messiah;</hi> against whom you stand in Rebellion to this day.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:31868:28"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 8. And was not this fulfilled when the <hi>Messiah</hi> rid into <hi>Jerusalem</hi> upon the Foal of an Ass? <hi>Out of the Mouthes of Babes and Sucklings hast thou ordained Strength.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And did not the <hi>Messiah</hi> say these words when you put him to Death? Psal. 31. <hi>Into thy Hands I commend my Spirit: And thou hast brought my Soul out of the Grave, thou hast revived me from them that go down into the Pit; sing Praises unto the Lord ye his Saints.</hi> So the Saints can sing Praises unto the Lord, that know the Resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Messiah,</hi> whose Grave you watched; yet he rise, and all your Watch-men were struck: but your Priests taught them to Lye, and to say, <hi>His Disciples stole him away:</hi> In which Lye, and Graves of Sin and Unbelief you lie, that do not believe the <hi>Messiah</hi> is come, and is risen, <hi>Psal.</hi> 30.3.</p>
               <p>And was not this the Doctrine of the <hi>Messiah</hi> to your Fore-Fathers, <hi>That
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:31868:28"/> the Meek Men should possess the Earth, and have their Delight in the multitude of Peace; but the Wicked practiseth against the Just, and gnashes his Teeth against him.</hi> And was not this the Practice of your Fore-Fathers against the Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siah? <hi>Psal.</hi> 37.12.</p>
               <p>And in <hi>Psal.</hi> 78. <hi>I will open my Mouth in Parables; I will declare high Sentences of Old.</hi> And did not the Messiah ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil these Sayings, and declare the high Sentences of Old, and speak in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables when he came?</p>
               <p>And in <hi>Psal.</hi> 82. where it is said, <hi>I have said ye are Gods, and ye all are Children of the Most High.</hi> And did not your Fore-Fathers persecute and put to Death the Messiah for saying, <hi>He was the Son of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in <hi>Psal.</hi> 91. <hi>He shall give his Angels Charge over thee, to keep thee in all thy Wayes; they shall bear thee in their Hands, that thou hurt not thy Foot against a Stone.</hi> And was not the Messiah tryed and tempted by Satan and you
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:31868:29"/> in your dayes, wherein that Scripture was fulfilled upon him, when Satan Tempted him, and perverted those words.</p>
               <p>And in <hi>Psal.</hi> 10. where it is said, <hi>The Lord said unto my Lord, Sit thou on my Right Hand, until I make thy Enemies thy Foot stool.</hi> Is not this the <hi>Messiah,</hi> and the <hi>Immanuel,</hi> born of a Virgin, spoken of <hi>Esaiah,</hi> which came and said to your Fore-Fathers above Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Hundred Years since, <hi>If</hi> David <hi>in Spirit called the</hi> Messiah <hi>Lord, how was he his Son?</hi> which neither your Fore-Fathers nor you ever answerd?</p>
               <p>Also, <hi>The Lord Sware, and will not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>epent; Thou art a Priest forever, after the Order of</hi> Melchizedeck. Now was not this the <hi>Messiah,</hi> who came not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Order of <hi>Aaron,</hi> which had a Beginning of Dayes and End of Life; but he, the <hi>Messiah,</hi> is a Priest forever after the Order of <hi>Melchizedeck,</hi> is without Beginning of Days or End of Life.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:31868:29"/>
               <p>And is not the Prophecy of <hi>Isaiah</hi> 5. fulfilled upon you, where he saith, The Vineyard is laid waste, and you which were the Keepers of it, who stoned the Servants, and had killed the Son, the Heir; and now are you and your Vineyard laid waste? And did not the <hi>Messiah</hi> when he came shew you the fulfilling of the Prophecy in this? and so is not your Sun and Moon darkned, and your Stars fallen, as you may read in the Prophets? and the Marvelous Work the Lord hath done upon you, and a Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? For the Wisdom of your Wise Men is perished; for the Lord hath covered you with the Spirit of Slum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and hath shut up your Eyes, and the Vision is become unto you as the words of a Sealed Book, so that you can neither read the Book of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets nor of the Law, that speak of the <hi>Messiah,</hi> being out of the Spirit. Though you come near unto the Lord
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:31868:30"/> with your Mouthes, and honour him with your Lips, but have removed your Hearts far from him; and your Fear towards him is taught by the Precepts of Men: And this did <hi>Isai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> fore-see and prophesie of; and this did the <hi>Messiah</hi> see and find amongst you when he came.</p>
               <p>And in <hi>Isa.</hi> 54. it is said, <hi>All thy Children shall be taught of the Lord.</hi> And did not the <hi>Messiah</hi> when he came show the Fulfilling of this Prophecy, so that many Thousands are Witnesses of God's Teaching, and his establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them in Peace?</p>
               <p>And was not the Saying of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah</hi> the Prophet fulfilled, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7. <hi>Is this House become a Den of Thieves whereupon my Name is called before your Eyes? behold I see it saith the Lord.</hi> And was not this fulfilled in the days of the Messiah, above Sixteen Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years since? And did not the Lord say, <hi>Therefore I will cast you out of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:31868:30"/> my Sight, as I have cast out your Brethren before you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in <hi>Hosea</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. did not the Lord say, <hi>He desired Mercy, and not Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; and the Knowledge of God more then Burnt-Offerings: But ye like men have transgressed the Covenant, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have ye trespassed against me; and as Thieves wait for a Man, so do the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Priests murder in the Way by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent; for they work Mischief.</hi> Now was not this fulfilled in the dayes of the Messiah? Were not the Priests the most Mischievous against him? Did they not gather together in Troops to work Mischief against him, and to put him to Death? And had you had Mercy, and the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, you would have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Messiah when he came, the Son, born of a Virgin?</p>
               <p>And again, In a <hi>Esdras</hi> Chap. 1. Vers. 30. <hi>The Lord gathered you as a Hen gathereth her Chicken under her
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:31868:31"/> Wings: But now what shall I do for you? I will cast you out of my Sight.</hi> And would not the Messiah have gathered you when he came, and you would not. So that your House is become a Desolation, and you cast forth.</p>
               <p>And in the Sayings of the Wisdom of <hi>Solomon</hi> Chap. 2. <hi>He checks us for offending against the Law; he makes his Boast to have the Knowledge of God; he calls himself the Son of God: He is made to reprove our Thoughts: it grieves us also to look upon him; for his Life is not like other mens, his Wayes are of another Fashion: Let us examine him with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes and Torments, that we may know his Meekness and prove his Patience; let us condemn him to a shameful Death.</hi> And did not you <hi>Jews</hi> fulfil all this? and are no these Sayings verified by you concerning the Messiah?</p>
               <p>And you Sons of <hi>Adam,</hi> who are called <hi>Jews,</hi> what do you think of the Saying in <hi>Esdras?</hi> Chap. 7. <hi>The
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:31868:31"/> Bride shall appear, and she shall come forth and be seen, that now is under the Earth: For my Son</hi> JESUS <hi>shall appear with those that be with him, and they that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main shall Rejoyce within Four Hundred Years; and after these same Years shall my Son</hi> CHRIST <hi>Dye.</hi> So do ye think he spoak Truth? And what <hi>Jesus</hi> was this, the anointed, that was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesied of should dye after the Four Hundred Years?</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>G. F.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:31868:32"/>
            <head>FOR THE JEWS Who Assemble in Bevers-Marks, LONDON; To be Read and Considered by them.</head>
            <p>DO you pretend to adore the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting <hi>Jehovah;</hi> and have not Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to hear a few words in his Name and Power, by one of his Faithfull Servants and Messengers in your Assembly? What God do you serve? are you affraid your God should fail you, or that you should be stagger'd with the Words of the True God? I Came in Tenderness of Heart, in
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:31868:32"/> Travail of Spirit, and in Love to your Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Souls among you, and patiently wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted till you had ended your Devotion, and then told you, <hi>I had a few words to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare unto you in the Name of the Everlasting Jehovah;</hi> earnestly desiring your Audience, pressing you to shew so much Humanity and Moderation as to hear me when you began to Bussle Scorn and make a Noise against me: And after I further urged to be heard as you would Answer the Great <hi>Jehovah;</hi> telling you, <hi>what I had to declare was accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to</hi> Moses <hi>and the Prophets</hi> you further made a hiddeous Noyse, Bauling, Singing, Canting, Scoffing, Contemning, and the Like; some endeavouring to hale, Shove and pull me down, Crying, <hi>this is not a place, &amp;c.</hi> I calling aloud to you, <hi>Repent, Repent, Repent, &amp;c.</hi> upon this your Course and uncivil entertainment, and I having used the words of <hi>Moses, To hearken to the Voice of God, and his Word which is very near thee even in thine heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. Isaiah 2.</note>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the Words of the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> to your Revolted Fore-Fathers <hi>O house of</hi> Jacob, <hi>come ye and let us walk in the Light of the Lord:</hi> One of your Company (by me) most Contempteously and Blasphemously Answered, LET US
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:31868:33"/> WALK IN THE DARKNESS OF THE LORD, By all which both your Ungodly and Inhuman Proceedings and Posture you shewed your selves partakers of that persecuting Spirit which Ruled in your Fore-Fathers, and acted them against the holy Prophets, Servants and Messengers of God, and it was that Rebellious perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting spirit which occasion'd those many and great Miseries, Desolations, Thraldoms, and Contempts to come upon them and their Posterities from the Just Hand of God for their wickedness, Pride, Persecution and Rebellion against him and his Servants. And why would you not here me speak a few words of Truth and Soberness in the Great <hi>Jehovah's</hi> Name, and that out of tender Love to your immortal Souls, and a serious Respect to the Everlasting State and Good thereof? And why was it that you would not so hear me at that time and place? was it because of that Holiness of your Sabbath, or Sanctity of your Synagogue or Place? was your Zeal such for the Observation and Reverence of both, and yet at both time and place you could take Liberty to behave your selves irreverently against God's Truth tendred to you; and uncivility and wickedly against his Servant, (as before hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:31868:33"/> and yet you know that it is but by Toleration or Connivance that you have your Liberty for the publick Exercise of your Ceremonial devotion although you thus abuse it: what might we Expect from you if you had Power in your Hands? can you suppose that you have acted for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation or credit of your selves or Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in your deportment towards us? The mighty <hi>Jehovah</hi> will Reprove and Judge you, you Earth-Worms, you Coveteous Persons, you Sensual Men, you Carnal fleshly People, you Scorners, you Dispisers, you Proud Imperious Hypocrites, your hearts are Remote from God while you pretend to honour him with your Lips; it is but from your teeth outward, not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allity: you have not only put Vails over your heads, but the Vail of sin Darkness and Corruption over your hearts: you have not only stopt your outward Ears against the sound of Truth which should have been published and heard among you, But also the inward ear of your Soul have you stopt against the <hi>Immediate inward and Souls Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Word and Ʋoice of God under all your outward Noises, Cantations, Singings, feigned Tonos, Charmes, Ceremonies</hi> (which cannot save your Souls) fleshly adorations Car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:31868:34"/> Cringings; glorying in the Flesh in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side Appearances &amp; fleshly Shews, to be seen &amp; wondred at by men; as though the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Jehovah</hi> had need of the works of your hands or fleshly performances, while your hearts are far from him; being Impenitent and hard, you want Contrition of heart and the Brokenness of Spirit before the Lord, which is the sacrifice well-pleasing to him, you tremble not at his word. You con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side in Shadows, and neglect the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, Inward Word, Light and Life of God the Lord (the Everlasting <hi>Jehovah</hi>) unto which <hi>Moses</hi> and the Prophets testified, and exhorted <hi>Israel;</hi> this you Carelesly over-look and neglect; while your Flesh makes a Noise, and Glories in Shews and Appearances, you hear not the Voice of God, you hearken not to it: The small still Voice or word that comes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, you heed not, you attend not to it, you hear it not in your Noises and Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations; for it is heard inwardly, in the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of all Flesh, where the mind is stay'd upon God, and the Soul seriously, retired, and inwardly waits in the Light of the Lord, the God of <hi>Jacob.</hi> Therefore be still; and wait upon the Lord; O all Flesh be silent at his Presence that your Souls may hear his
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:31868:34"/> Voice and live; <hi>Hearken unto me, saith the Lord, hour, and your Souls shall Live;</hi> the Word or Voice of the Lord is lively and powerful; his Voice shook the Earth; at his Voice the Earth melted his Word mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the hoary Frosts, and he by his Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings enlightened the World, and the Earth saw and Trembled: O all flesh fear &amp; Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before him; for all flesh is as the Grass which withereth when the Spirit of the Lord blowes upon it.</p>
            <p>It was the Sin of your Fore-Fathers to disobey the <hi>Immediate Voice of God,</hi> to grieve and vex his good (and holy) Spirit, which he gave unto them, and to place their Dignity, Merits, Righteousness, Religion and Devotion in their natural Descent of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, and out-side Appearances and shadowy things of the Law, which could not afford Divine Life nor inward Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief to their Immortal Souls, nor make the Observers perfect as to the Conscience; for both <hi>Moses</hi> and the Prophets, even in the time of the Outward Dispensation of Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows under the Law, had an Eye to the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery and Substance all along, with respect to the Everlasting State and Good of the Soul: And therefore its said to <hi>Israel, Thou shalt turn</hi> into thine Heart <hi>among all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:31868:35"/> whether the Lord thy God hath driven thee, and shalt return unto the Lord thy God, and shalt obey his Voice.</hi> And its after said, <hi>The Lord thy God will circumcise thine Heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.</note>
               <hi>and the Heart of thy Seed, to love the Lord thy God with all thine Heart, and with all thy Soul, that thou mayst live.</hi> This Circumcision of the Heart made of God, is beyond your outward Circumcision of the Flesh (which you glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in.) And the Prophet <hi>David</hi> said, <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices &amp; Burnt-Offerings thou requirest not</hi>— But the Sacrifices of God are a Contrite Heart, and a Broken Spirit; these were above and beyond those many Outward Sacrifices, Oblations and Burnt-Offerings in the Law, and by the Priesthood of <hi>Levi.</hi> And its said, <hi>Wash ye, make you clean, put away the Evil of your Doings from before mine Eyes:</hi> This is an Inward &amp; Spiritual Washing, a Soul-cleans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Conscience purifying, above the divers and carnal Washings imposed by the Law, which could not purifie the Conscience; This Inward Purity of Heart, being awanting in your Fore-Fathers, while they disobey'd the Voice of God (as you do) and their set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling themselves, and taking up a Rest in their Outward Observations, and their not cying the Lord, the Fountain of Life, nor
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:31868:35"/> attending upon his Spirit, Word and Voice within (but Forsaking him) for these the Lord rebuked them, and rejected their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, Sacrifices and Worships, saying, <hi>To what Purpose is the multitude of your Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices unto me; I am full of the Burnt-Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Rams, and the Fat of Fed Beasts; I delight not in the Blood of Bullocks or of Lambs, &amp;c. when ye come to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before me?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 1.11.</note>
               <hi>Who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired this at your Hands? Bring no more vain Oblations; The New Moons and Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths I cannot away with, it is Iniquity: Your New Moons and your appointed Feasts my Soul hateth, they are a Trouble unto me; and when ye spread forth your Hand, I will hide mine Eyes from you; yea, when ye make many Prayers, I will not hear; your Hands are full of Blood: Wash ye, make you Clean, &amp;c.</hi> Also, its further testified against them, <hi>He that killeth an Ox,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 66.3.</note>
               <hi>as if he slew a Man; he that sacrificeth a Lamb, as if he cut off a Dog's Neck; he that offereth an Oblation, as if he offered Swin's Blood; he that burneth Incense, as if he blessed an Idol; yea, they have chosen their own Way, and their Souls delight in their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations.</hi> And how can you think your selves any more accepted of God in your
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:31868:36"/> Dead Ceremonies and empty Shews and Shadows? Now as the Inward circumcisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the inward Sacrifice, the inward Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing of the Heart were above those Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Ones (And <hi>I desire Mercy, and not Sacrifice</hi>) So there was an Inward and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Temple (wherein God dwells in his People) which he preferred and doth esteem beyond your Fathers Outward Temple: Therefore said the Prophet <hi>Jeremy, Trust ye not in Lying Words, saying, The Temple of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 7.4, 5.</note>
               <hi>The Temple of the Lord</hi> (whereas) <hi>the Temple of the Lord are these, If ye throughly amend your Wayes and your Doings, &amp;c.</hi> Such as these, who amended their Wayes and their Doings, were his <hi>Temple.</hi> Thus saith the Lord, Isa. 66.1, 2. <hi>The Heaven is my Throne, and the Earth is my Foot-stool; Where is the House that ye Build unto me? and where is the Place of my Rest? for all these things hath mine Hand made—But to this man will I look, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to him that is Poor, and of a Contrite Spirit, and Trembleth at my Word.</hi> Mark these things, and turn into your Hearts, and with the Light of the God of <hi>Jacob</hi> do you search and examine your selves, that you may see the Hardness of your Hearts and your Impenitency, how full and puft up
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:31868:36"/> you are, how far distant from the State of God's spiritual House or Temple, and how much unmeet for his Dwelling-place: You are too high for God; your Pride, Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy, Wilfulness and Hardness of Heart do make you unlike God's House and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; you partake of the Rebellion of your Apostate Disobedient Fore-Fathers, which occasioned their Miseries, Desolations, and Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>persion among the Nations, and their Bondage and Subjection under Strangers, as was fore-told by the Holy Prophets, and a Remembrance of the Fruits of that Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion is to be seen upon you and your People (as Partakers of their Sin) to this day. And finally, The great Destruction and Havock of your Metropolitan City <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and the Temple thereof &amp;c. (by <hi>Titus,</hi> or the <hi>Gentiles</hi>) which was foretold<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37, 38. <hi>Luke</hi> 19.41, 42, 43, 44 &amp; 143.3. <hi>Mark</hi> 13.1, 2. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.5, 6.</note> by that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Prophet or man Jesus, whom your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Fore-Fathers of that Age envied, and they with their Priests deliver'd unto the Rulers of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> and People, and him they persecuted and put to Death by
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:31868:37"/> that cruel Torture of Crucifixion, according to the <hi>Romans</hi> Law, made for Notorious Malefactors and Treasonable Persons, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom he was Numbred, according to that Saying and Prophecy of him in <hi>Isa.</hi> 53. But on the Consideration of that sore De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction and Misery, fore told by this Man Jesus, which justly came upon your Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Predecessors and their great City, ought not your Spirits rather to be bowed down, and you Humbled, then to entertain any Evil Opinions of him (or them who sincerely esteem him) meerly from Reports and Traditions of your Rebellious Fore-Fathers, or his Prejudiced Persecutors and Enemies, whom God for their Sins and Provocations justly brought the Scourge upon, as was plainly foretold by this despi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Prophet.</p>
            <div type="questions">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:31868:37"/>
               <head>And now, I being not desirous to impose a Faith upon you [as from bare Asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion] concerning this Great Prophet, but first, to remove your Prejudice, that you may come into a serious Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and a right Understanding, I propose these few <hi>Questions</hi> for you, desiring your plain <hi>Answer,</hi> after your deliberate Consideration.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Question</hi> I. May you not Reasonably suspect or believe, that your Rebellious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessors and Fore-Fathers did greatly incur God's Displeasure against themselves by their Implocable Envy and Deadly Instiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions against this Jesus (who was called Christ) with other their great Provocations; seeing Misery and Ruin came upon them at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> according as was foretold by him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> II. May you not also reasonably sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that their Imprecation was fulfill'd upon them, which they made to accomplish their Bloddy Designe upon Jesus in their saying, <hi>His Blood be upon us and our Children?</hi> What
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:31868:38"/> more signal Token of the fulfilling hereof could here appear then that miserable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction which afterwards came upon them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> III. Did not your Fore-Fathers greatly violate the Law of Equity (viz. <hi>Thou shalt love thy Neighbour as thy self</hi>) when they were so Partial and Cruelly-min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded towards this said True Prophet and his Followers (called <hi>Christians</hi>) when they would not endure they should enjoy the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of their Consciences or their Lives, in the Exercise of their Religion?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> IV. And had not those your Fore-Fathers their own Liberty, then for their publick Devotion and Religion by Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on under the <hi>Romish</hi> Empire, and yet would not allow the same Liberty to others (as to Jesus and his Followers) but instigated the Rulers of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and the People a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them; for those Persecuting <hi>Jews</hi> had not then Power to put any Man to Death, as they confessed?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> V. And what Reason can you have to believe such partial and cruel Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>secutors against Jesus and his Followers? or to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Unbelief, Evil (or Prejudiced) Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:31868:38"/> against Him or <hi>His,</hi> from the Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Reports of such their implacable Ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mies (who were for their Iniquities dreadfully Overthrown, as was foretold by Jesus) there does not yet appear to us any Reason to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse you herein? Answer it how you can.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> VI. And what can you pretend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him, but such things as those his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious Persecutors and Murderers did? Have you not the same or such like Opinions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him, that those your Fore-Fathers had, as that he was <hi>a Sinner, a Blasphemer, a Caster-out of Devils by</hi> Beelzebub, <hi>that he would have made himself a Worldly Prince, or King of the</hi> Jews, <hi>that he was guilty of Death?</hi> Have you any Worse then these against him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> VII. And what say you of <hi>John Baptist,</hi> who highly testified for this (Great Prophet) Jesus, as the <hi>Messiah?</hi> Have you not a worse Opinion of <hi>John</hi> then your fore-Fathers had, who esteemed of him as a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> VIII. And can Reason or Equity admit such, as either competent Witnesses, or equal Judges against Jesus, whose Hatred
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:31868:39"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:31868:39"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:31868:40"/> and Prejudice was such; that notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the many convincing Signs, Wonders and Miracles which God did by him, yet they wilfully Opposed and resisted him and his Testimony, as those that had both seen and hated him and his Father?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q</hi> IX. And have you any Opinion against his Resurrection but what still pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from your Fore-Fathers his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and Persecutors, viz. the Chief Priests and Elders from what they caused the mercenary Souldiers (for Reward) to Report who watched his Sepulchre?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> X. And is not still this Report be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved among you (as it was among your sinful Fore-Fathers) to wit, <hi>That the Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Jesus came by Night and stole him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, (out of the Sepulchre) while the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers (that watched) him slept?</hi> and by whose Means did those Souldiers report this, but his Enemies, who were a Party combin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed against him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> XI. Was not your Scepter of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment removed from you, your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom Rent and torn (did it not depart from <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h</hi>) when your <hi>Metrapollitan</hi> City
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:31868:40"/>
                  <hi>Jerusalem</hi> was spoiled and laid wast by <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus?</hi> If you say it is not (or never yet) departed; then I ask:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> XII. Where did your said Scepter continue till this day? and where is it? where a now the Scepter of your Government and Common wealth?</p>
               <p>I desire your plain and direct <hi>Answer</hi> to these <hi>Questions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And withal, to understand, that we the People of <hi>Jehovah,</hi> called <hi>Quakers</hi> (who have trembled at his Word, according to that Saying of the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> 66.2.) do Own but One True, Living, Eternal God; <hi>The Lord thy God is One Lord; the Lord is One, and his Name One</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">This may import to you (to remove Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice) that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> do not profes. Three Gods.</note> though there be several Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestations &amp; Out-goings of this One God [or Eternal Word, which in Time took Flesh] And the spiritual bringing forth of his Son in his People, as God's own Likeness, Wisdom, divine Life, Spirit and Power, we are Witnesses of: So the Father, the Son, and Spirit, are One in Beeing. Also, see <hi>Isaiah</hi> 9.6. where the Son is called, the <hi>Mighty God,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:31868:41"/> The Everlasting Father, &amp;c.</hi> And we are come unto the New and Everlasting Covenant,<note place="margin">See Isa. 44.13. Jer. 31.31, 33, 34.</note> wherein all are taught of God; <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>By a Friend and Lover of your Immortal Souls, who desires their Everlasting Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity (in Derision called a</hi> Quaker) <hi>G. W.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>The 17th of the 8th Moneth, 1674.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>This was written in the 10th Moneth [only some few words added] a little time after I was among the <hi>Jews,</hi> in the Year, according to our <hi>English</hi> Account, 1671. But no Answer thereunto have we yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>